we are going to talk about the four most
important concepts the four pillars of
object oriented programming and those
are encapsulation inheritance
abstraction and polymorphism now i know
those words might sound very
intimidating at first but trust me when
i say that the actual concepts behind
those scary words are actually very easy
to understand but before you continue
watching make sure you watch the first
video i posted about oop because there i
wanted to introduce oop in a more
practical way i wanted to show you how
oop helps you organize and reason about
your code without looking into the
theory too much but in this video we are
going to look into the theory of oop
because that's something that you might
need in a coding interview so let's get
started with encapsulation encapsulation
is the idea of placing data and
functions that use the data inside of a
container inside of a capsule in our
case the capsules are classes take this
example here we have data which is an
elon mosque object and we also have a
function that calculates his net worth
by multiplying his shares with the share
price because the function and the data
are conceptually related we can improve
this code by using encapsulation with
encapsulation we will put the data and
the function inside of a class making
the code look something like this the
advantage now is that the code is more
organized and also the functions or
methods don't have to take any arguments
because they all have access to the data
of the class using this keyword using
encapsulation we can also choose what
properties of the class we want to
expose and which properties we want to
keep hidden in this case because all the
fields of the class are private no one
can access or modify them from the
outside this is why this code won't work
encapsulation gives us the power to
decide how the information about the
class should be accessed or modified so
for example if you want to expose the
name of our entrepreneur we can make a
method to do so all the examples on this
video are typescript codes by the way if
you know javascript but you don't know
typescript please click the link below
to learn it for free with me and with
subtitles in google typescript makes
javascript developers more productive
happier and less stressed so if you want
to be like that please click the link
below where you will find a typescript
course i will see you there
and that's it that is encapsulation it
is the act of organizing data and
functions that use that data inside of
classes and thanks to that we are able
to do data hiding which allows us to
choose which data to expose and which
data to hide next we have inheritance we
saw inheritance on the first oop video
that we made but anyways we're going to
look at it again inheritance allows us
to divide our code in smaller classes in
smaller units and to reuse them if apart
from having an entrepreneur class we
also want to have an actor class our
actor class will also need to have first
name and last name just like the
entrepreneur class does without
inheritance we will have to create two
separate classes with two duplicate
first name and last name properties if
we take a look at the code that doesn't
look so good using inheritance since we
know that the entrepreneur and the actor
classes both need a first name and a
last name we can move those duplicate
properties first name and last name to
another class called person and then we
can say that both entrepreneur and actor
both inherit the first name and last
name from the personal class we do this
by using the extends keyword in
typescript the syntax to extend a class
changes between languages but the
concept is the same by extending a class
the child class will inherit or receive
all the properties from the parent class
this means that now entrepreneur and
person classes both have first and last
name properties and also this means that
if we implement the say hi method in the
person class both our entrepreneur and
our actor classes will also be able to
say hello inheritance allows us to
divide and conquer with inheritance we
can divide our classes into small pieces
and we can compose them as if they were
lego blocks let's now keep going with
abstraction the father of c plus plus
defines abstraction as the act of
specifying a general interface hiding
implementation
details
with that definition and before jumping
into the code let's look at some
examples of abstraction in the real
world when you drive a car you are using
an interface to control the car that
interface the steering wheel and the
pedals and the buttons all those things
are exposed by the maker of the car so
we can use that interface to communicate
with the machine
the car interface hides the
implementation details from the driver
which means that you are able to drive
the car without actually knowing how the
engine works internally
all that is hidden from you for a code
example let's build our own abstraction
let's say that we don't like the way we
work with arrays in javascript so we
want to build our own abstraction on top
of them for this let's create a class
called better array better array will
have an array inside of it but instead
of exposing the array we are going to
create and expose methods as an
interface to interact with the array in
a more comfortable way this class will
have methods to get add remove and
modify items inside of the array
now when someone uses our better array
they just have to use the methods we
exposed as an interface to interact with
the array they don't have to know the
implementation details of each method
and for example they need to know how
index off or filter works and just like
that we created our own abstraction we
defined a general interface for a better
array hiding the implementation details
another big benefit of using abstraction
is that if tomorrow for example i change
the way modify item method works to make
it faster
no one that is using the modify method
will have to change anything because
even though the implementation change
the interface remains the same now to
finish this let's talk about
polymorphism poly means multiple like
polygons many sites and morphos means
shape or form like amorphous something
without a form or morphology the study
of the shape of the words so
polymorphism multiple forms multiple
shapes to understand polymorphism in oop
we have to remember that with
inheritance all the properties and
methods of the parent class go to the
child class as well in this example both
the hangukin and the italian classes
extend from a person class
this means that objects from the
hangukin class and italian class both
have the method say hi
polymorphism comes into play when i want
my hangouting class to extend from
person but i want my hangouting class to
change the way it says hi for this we
would have to write our own say hi
method in the handguging class this is
called method overriding we use the same
name say hi but a different
implementation so now if we call the say
hi method from an object from the
handbooking class it will say hello in a
different way than if we call the say
hive method from a member of the italian
class but that is not all with
polymorphism the say high method of the
hanguking class should have the same
result as the one in the person class in
the person class the say hi method
returns a string
this means that if the handbook in class
that is extending from person wants to
override the say hive method it can do
so but it should also return a string if
i try to return a number from the say hi
method in the handbooking class
typescript will stop me because say hi
is not doing what it's supposed to be
doing which is returning a string and
that is polymorphism in oop as you can
see it allows us to override methods
from parent classes but it makes us a
strict two contracts on how the methods
should work this way the essence of the
class stays the same even though the
shape of the implementation is different
using polymorphism we can be sure that
both the hanging and the italian classes
say hello they just do it in a different
way and that's it for this video these
have been the four pillars of
object-oriented programming
encapsulation inheritance abstraction
and polymorphism if you found this video
useful then please leave a like and
subscribe it's free for you but it helps
me a lot and don't forget if you want to
learn to code for free with me and
subtitles in hangul please click the
link below there you're going to find
free javascript python go react react
native courses among many many other
things thank you so so much for watching
stay free stay healthy stay happy eat
kimchi kamzamira salang hayo see you in
the next one bye-bye
good
you